Inventory of the Dagmara Lejnieks collection, 1962-2012
Hoover Institution Archives
Dagmara Lejnieks collection
1962-2012
2012C53
Hoover Institution Archives
5 manuscript boxes, 1 card file box (2 linear feet)
The collection contains significant materials relating to the movement for Latvian (and Baltic) independence in the late perestroika era of the Soviet Union, as well as documents pertaining to the first year of the renewed Latvian state that emerged in 1991. These materials were selected by Lejnieks as her personal record of a time that is often referred to by Latvians as simply "The Barricades," a turbulent period that saw barricades erected in the Latvian capital Rîga and the killing of demonstrators by Soviet security forces (OMON troops). The materials in the Lejnieks collection include clippings, correspondence, serial issues, monographs, and video recordings. Most prominent among the serial issues are copies of the American Latvian newspaper Laiks, which provided extensive coverage of events in Latvia during this period. The articles in Laiks illustrate how the Latvian independence movement was perceived, encouraged, and criticized by the Latvian diaspora in North America, and other materials in the collection also show how the movement was depicted in the mainstream media of the United States.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2012.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical/Historical Note
1933 Born, Rîga, Latvia
1944-1945 As refugees, Lejnieks family leaves Latvia for Germany, where they live in Zwickau, near Dresden. They witness the Allied firebombing of Dresden in February, 1945 and their own house in Zwickau is bombed in March, 1945
1945-1948 Lives with family in a Displaced Persons camp in Dinkelsbühl, West Germany
1949-1950 Attends high school in Sillenbuch and Esslingen, West Germany
1950 Emigrates with family to the United States, settling in Southern California
1951 Graduates from Santa Ynez High School
1955 Graduates from San Jose State College with a bachelor's degree in medical technology
1956-1995 Works as a medical technologist at Palo Alto Medical Clinic
Scope and Content of Collection
The Dagmara Lejnieks collection contains significant materials relating to the movement for Latvian (and Baltic) independence in the late perestroika era of the Soviet Union, as well as documents pertaining to the first year of the renewed Latvian state that emerged in 1991. These materials were selected by Lejnieks as her personal record of a time that is often referred to by Latvians as simply "The Barricades," a turbulent period that saw barricades erected in the Latvian capital Rîga and the killing of demonstrators by Soviet security forces (OMON troops). The materials in the Lejnieks collection include clippings, correspondence, serial issues, monographs, and video recordings. Most prominent among the serial issues are copies of the American Latvian newspaper Laiks, which provided extensive coverage of events in Latvia during this period. The articles in Laiks illustrate how the Latvian independence movement was perceived, encouraged, and criticized by the Latvian diaspora in North America, and other materials in the collection also show how the movement was depicted in the mainstream media of the United States.
In addition, the collection has copies of Akadçmiskâ dzîve, an important journal published by the Latvian community in the United States and in which both political topics and more general cultural issues are discussed. There are also some texts and a flyer published by the American Latvian Association that exemplify the kind of activity undertaken by this organization as part of its campaign for Latvian independence during the Cold War. The video recordings in the collection include some broadcasts relating to the official celebration of Latvian independence day in 1991, as well as some television broadcasts of concerts of Latvian music.
Latvia--Politics and government.; Latvians--United States.; Video tapes.
- Personal file, 1991 (Folder 1: 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Contains autobiographical writing, letters to Dagmara Lejnieks, and clippings
- Serial issues and other printed matter, 1962-2012 (Box 1)
  Contains newspapers, magazines, monographs, and a poster/flyer
  - Laiks, 1990-1991 (Box 1)
    - 1990 (Box 1)
      - February-April (Folder 1: 2)
      - May (Folder 1: 3)
      - June-August (Folder 1: 4)
    - 1991 (Box 1)
      - January (Folder 1: 5)
      - February (Folder 1: 6)
      - March (Folder 2: 1)
      - April (Folder 2: 2)
      - May (Folder 2: 3)
      - June (Folder 2: 4)
      - July (Folder 2: 5)
      - August (Folder 3: 1)
      - September (Folder 3: 2)
      - October (Folder 3: 3)
      - November (Folder 3: 4)
      - December (Folder 3: 5)
  - The Latvians: Their Culture and Art, poster/flyer published by the American Latvian Association, 1962 (Folder 3: 6)
  - Latvia, published by the American Latvian Association, 1968 (Folder 3: 7)
  - Dziesmu svçtku gara gaita, 1990 (Folder 3: 8)
  - Latvija sodien, 1991 (Folder 3: 9)
  - Latvija Baltijas valsts, 1991/1992 (Folder 3: 10)
  - Akadçmiskâ dzîve, nos. 17-48, 1975-2011/2012 (Folder 4: 1-32)
- Video recordings, 1990-1993. (Box 5)
  Contains 5 VHS video cassettes
  - "Mâjâs: Dziesmu svçtki Rîga 1990," Latvijas Informâcijas Televîzija (Folder 5: 1)
  - Clips of American television news broadcasts relating to the Soviet Union and the Latvian independence movement, 1990-1991 (Folder 5: 2)
  - "18. Novembra koncerts,", 1991 November 18 (Folder 5: 3)
  - "Ârpus Latvijas komponçta Latvieðu vokâli instrumentâlâm ûzika,", 1993 January 25. (Folder 5: 4)
    Includes booklet with texts
  - "Labdarîbas koncerts Opera,", 1993 (Folder 5: 5)